Troubleshooting anything involves a process,
and with networking, it is no different.
As this course is geared toward networking
for small to medium-sized businesses, there
are some steps we as network administrators
should use when troubleshooting a networking
situation.
Troubleshooting is basically a seven-step
process.
Step one is to identify the problem.
In this, we probably need to ask open-ended
questions to try to figure out why, for example,
a network connection is not working.
Is the problem isolated to one user?
Is an entire building affected?
A problem cannot be solved unless we know
what the problem is.
Step two: Establish a theory of probable cause;
this is a fancy way of saying, let's find
out what caused the problem.
Did something get unplugged?
Is there a misconfiguration?
Was a rogue device added to the network to
cause a network attack?
Step three: Test the theory.
Can we duplicate the problem?
If we can, it might make it easier to find
a solution.
Step four is to establish a plan to solve
the problem.
Is this an easy fix?
Are we going to need to reboot a server or
do something else that will disrupt services
temporarily?
To solve a problem, we need to have an idea
as to how to solve it.
Step five is to implement the solution or
escalate it as necessary.
Here, we need to understand a very important
point: If you are the one trying to solve
a problem and get stuck as to how to it, escalate
it.
Most network problems are very time-sensitive,
and taking too much time to fix something
when someone else can do it faster can cause
major problems in timing, data loss, lost
revenue, and frustrated employees.
Step six is to verify that the solution worked.
Before declaring to a customer that a problem
is solved, test out the solution.
Make sure that the original problem cannot
be replicated.
Lastly, step seven: Document the solution.
Many companies use some kind of help desk
ticketing software, SharePoint site, or even
a database to track problems and solutions.
Make sure a solution is detailed enough so
that someone else, should they encounter the
same problem, has an idea of what to do.